<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://www.mhira.app/blog</id>
    <title>MHIRA Blog</title>
    <updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.mhira.app/blog"/>
    <subtitle>MHIRA Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://www.mhira.app/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Celebrating Our Publication in BMC Psychiatry - The MHIRA Project]]></title>
        <id>/2023/10/02/achieving-publication-in-bmc-psychiatry-mhira-project</id>
        <link href="https://www.mhira.app/blog/2023/10/02/achieving-publication-in-bmc-psychiatry-mhira-project"/>
        <updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce a significant milestone for the Mental Health Information Reporting Assistant (MHIRA) project – our recent publication in BMC Psychiatry, a prestigious journal in the field of mental health. This publication marks a pivotal moment in our journey, emphasizing the importance of evidence-based assessment (EBA) in mental health care and showcasing the potential of MHIRA as a transformative tool in this domain.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce a significant milestone for the Mental Health Information Reporting Assistant (MHIRA) project – our recent publication in BMC Psychiatry, a prestigious journal in the field of mental health. This publication marks a pivotal moment in our journey, emphasizing the importance of evidence-based assessment (EBA) in mental health care and showcasing the potential of MHIRA as a transformative tool in this domain.</p><p><a href="https://bmcpsychiatry.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12888-023-05201-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" alt="BMC Article" src="/assets/images/MHIRA_BMC-d768557896ef9bd1c68527ee3264bcf7.png" width="1536" height="1138" class="img_E7b_"></a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="the-importance-of-our-bmc-psychiatry-publication">The Importance of Our BMC Psychiatry Publication<a class="hash-link" href="#the-importance-of-our-bmc-psychiatry-publication" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Our article, titled "Mental Health Information Reporting Assistant (MHIRA)—an open-source software facilitating evidence-based assessment for clinical services," provides a comprehensive overview of MHIRA and its implementation across various clinical settings. Here's a brief abstract to give you a glimpse into our research:</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="abstract">Abstract<a class="hash-link" href="#abstract" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Evidence-based assessment (EBA) in mental health is crucial for improving patient outcomes and addressing care gaps. However, its implementation faces significant challenges, especially in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). The MHIRA project introduces an open-source electronic health record system designed to streamline EBA by digitizing psychometric instruments and organizing patient data efficiently. This paper details MHIRA's features, technical aspects, and insights from its implementation, highlighting its potential to simplify EBA use in diverse clinical contexts and contribute to global mental health improvement.</p><p>Read the full article on BMC Psychiatry: <a href="https://bmcpsychiatry.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12888-023-05201-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mental Health Information Reporting Assistant (MHIRA) in BMC Psychiatry</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters<a class="hash-link" href="#why-this-matters" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The publication in BMC Psychiatry not only validates the scientific rigor and potential impact of the MHIRA project but also significantly contributes to the global dialogue on mental health care. It underscores the necessity for innovative solutions like MHIRA to overcome barriers in the adoption of EBA, especially in settings where resources are scarce.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="our-journey-ahead">Our Journey Ahead<a class="hash-link" href="#our-journey-ahead" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This publication is a stepping stone for further research, development, and implementation of MHIRA in diverse clinical settings around the world. We are committed to enhancing MHIRA's functionality, ensuring it remains a relevant and powerful tool for mental health professionals globally.</p><p>We invite you to join us in this exciting journey toward transforming mental health care through innovation and evidence-based practices. For more information on MHIRA and our future initiatives, visit <a href="https://mhira.app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MHIRA's official website</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="mental health" term="mental health"/>
        <category label="open-source" term="open-source"/>
        <category label="technology" term="technology"/>
        <category label="publication" term="publication"/>
    </entry>
</feed>